fi.com 2015-06-23

# Fisher Investments | Privacy & Security

(This version of the privacy policy in effect as of December 27, 2013)

##  General

This privacy policy sets out how Fisher Investments collects, uses and shares information concerning users of this website(individually “user” or “you”, collectively “users”).  Any changes to this privacy policy will be posted at [http://www.fisherinvestments.com/about/privacy-security/us](http://www.fi.com/about/privacy-security/us).  Users can also access this privacy policy via our homepage and from the bottom of every page by clicking on the appropriate link in the footer.

Fisher Investments and its associated companies are committed to respecting users’ privacy.  We have structured our website so that, in general, users can visit Fisher Investments on the web without identifying themselves or revealing any personal information.  Once users choose to provide Fisher Investments with any information by which users can be identified, users can be assured that it will only be collected, used and shared in accordance with this privacy policy. We encourage you to periodically review this privacy policy and any revisions thereto to ensure that you are familiar with the most current version.

##  Background

Fisher Investments is registered with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (the “SEC”) as an investment adviser, and is required to comply with SEC Regulation S-P (“Reg. S-P”), as well as the U.S. Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act of 1999 (the “GLB Act”). Reg. S-P and the GLB Act require Fisher Investments to have policies and procedures in place to protect the security and confidentiality of the non-public personal information of consumers and customers, and to provide a privacy notice to such persons describing our privacy policies and procedures.

To ensure consumer privacy laws are not violated, Fisher Investments has adopted the policies and procedures described under the “Privacy Notice” heading below, which govern the activities of each officer, member, director, trustee and employee of Fisher Investments (collectively called the “Personnel”).

##  Glossary

“Consumer” – an individual or an individual's legal representative that obtains or has obtained a financial product or service to be used primarily for personal, household or family purposes. A person becomes a consumer even if a questionnaire or application is withdrawn or denied or an advisory agreement does not become effective.

“Customer” – a consumer that has an ongoing relationship with Fisher Investments, whereby Fisher Investments is providing one or more financial products or services to the consumer (e.g., an advisory client of Fisher Investments).

“Nonpublic personal information” –

  * All personally identifiable financial information.
  * While the GLB Act excludes publicly available information (e.g., a list of persons and their publicly listed telephone numbers), nonpublic personal information does include any list, description or other grouping of consumers (and publicly available information pertaining to them) derived using any nonpublic personally identifiable financial information that is not publicly available information.

##  Privacy Notice

This U.S. Privacy Notice describes how we collects, uses and shares information from or about you. We are committed to protecting your privacy and your non-public personal information. Please click here for Fisher Investments’ U.S. Privacy Notice: <http://www.fi.com/pdf/Privacy_Notice.pdf>

##  What information Fisher Investments collects

Fisher Investments may collect the following information:

  * Fisher Investments collects information from users who request information and/or information materials, including name, address, telephone number, email address and investment-related questions.
  * Fisher Investments collects relevant information on applications and resumes from prospective employees via our careers website.
  * Fisher Investments collects information provided orally and in writing via email, mail, online or in person from prospective clients, clients, prospective employees and employees.
  * Fisher Investments collects users’ domain type, IP address and clickstream data. Such information is only identifiable by users’ IP address and is not linked to users’ personal information.

##  How Fisher Investments uses and shares information collected

Fisher Investments may use the information for the following reasons:

  * Internal record keeping.
  * To improve products and services.
  * To follow up, either by email, phone or mail, with people who have requested information and/or materials.
  * To periodically send promotional email or mail about services, recent developments or other information which users may find interesting using the email address or mailing address which users have provided when requesting information and/or materials.
  * To access certain special features or areas of this website.
  * To evaluate prospective employees for positions, and to employ its personnel.
  * To analyze the financial situation of prospective clients and to provide investment advisory and management services to clients.
  * As otherwise permitted by law.
  * Pursuant to your request.

Fisher Investments may disclose information externally as permitted or required by law (such as to affiliates, service providers, and regulatory agencies), or where users have provided permission.  Fisher Investments will _not_ sell or lease users' personal information to third parties so they can market to users.

##  How to access and rectify information

Users may contact Fisher Investments at any time to request access to information Fisher Investments maintains about them, to rectify any inaccuracies in such information, or to say they no longer want to be contacted by Fisher Investments for direct marketing or other purposes.  Fisher Investments can be contacted by mail, email or telephone as follows:

Fisher Investments  
ATTN: Marketing – Privacy  
5525 NW Fisher Creek Drive  
Camas, Washington 98607  
USA  
1-800-851-8845

In each case, please ensure that full name and address are provided in exactly the form in which it was originally provided to Fisher Investments to avoid any possible confusion with a different user.

To unsubscribe from Fisher Investments’ email communications, send an email to [optout@fi.com](mailto:optout@fi.com). Please put “UNSUBSCRIBE” in the subject field and include the email address where you received the content, along with any additional email addresses you would like suppressed. We will do our best to prevent you from receiving our email content in the future.

##  Security

Fisher Investments is committed to ensuring that user information is secure. In order to prevent unauthorized access or disclosure, Fisher Investments has put in place suitable physical, electronic and managerial procedures to safeguard and secure information. Nevertheless, due to the nature of the Internet and Internet technologies, security and privacy risks cannot be eliminated and Fisher Investments cannot guarantee that users’ personal information will not be disclosed in ways not otherwise described in this privacy policy.

##  Other Websites

The Fisher Investments website may contain links to enable users to visit other websites of interest easily. However, once users have used these links to leave this site, users should note that Fisher Investments does not have any control over that other website. Therefore, Fisher Investments cannot be responsible for the protection and privacy of any information which users provide while visiting such sites and such sites are not governed by this privacy policy. Users should exercise caution and look at the privacy policy applicable to the website in question.

##  Cookie Policy

What is a “cookie”? A cookie is a small data file containing information, such as a link that a user clicked on, which is written to the user's hard drive by a web server and used to track the pages visited. Fisher Investments allows third party partner organizations to place cookies on its behalf to collect information about the behavior of users visiting Fisher Investments’ website, including domain type, IP address and clickstream data, and to remember choices users make to improve their experience. Such information may be identifiable by IP address, but not by users’ personal information. It does not contain personal information such as name, address, telephone number or email address. It also does not contain user passwords.

While cookies and similar tools can serve many functions, the cookies we use perform the following functions:

1\. Performance Cookies

These cookies collect information about how visitors use a website, for instance which pages visitors go to most often, and if they get error messages from web pages, so that we can track the usage of our website and analyze traffic patterns. These cookies don’t collect information that identifies a visitor other than by their IP address. These cookies are only used to improve how a website works.

2\. Functionality Cookies

These cookies allow the website to remember choices you make (such as your user name, language or the region you are in) and provide enhanced, more personal features or content. These cookies can also be used to remember changes you have made to text size, fonts and other parts of web pages that you can customize. They may also be used to provide services you have asked for such as watching a video. The information these cookies collect cannot track your browsing activity on other websites.

3\. Advertising Cookies

We serve advertisements on various websites using third party companies. When you click on one of our ads and are taken to our website, these companies may place third party cookies on your browser to make advertising more relevant based on your interactions with our website and other websites that you may visit.

##  “Do Not Track” Signals

Our website does not respond to “do not track” signals from users’ web browsers.

##  How to Manage Cookies

You can control your internet browser's settings to prevent your browser from accepting new cookies, have your browser notify you when you receive a new cookie, or disable (or re-enable) cookies altogether. However, because our website uses cookies, if you do disable cookies performance and functionality will be affected. You can control your browser’s cookie settings as follows:

_Microsoft Internet Explorer 6.0, 7.0, 8.0_

  * Click on ‘Tools’ at the top of your browser window and select ‘Internet Options’
  * In the options window navigate to the ‘Privacy’ tab
  * To disable cookies: Move the slider to the top to block all cookies
  * Note there are various levels of cookie enablement and disablement in Explorer. For more information on other cookie settings offered in Internet Explorer, refer to the following page from Microsoft: http://windows.microsoft.com/en-GB/windows-vista/Block-or-allow-cookies

_Microsoft Internet Explorer 9.0_

  * Click on ‘Tools’ at the top of your browser window and select ‘Safety’
  * Then click ‘Delete browsing history’.
  * Select the ‘Cookies’ check box, and then click ‘Delete’.
  * Note there are various levels of cookie enablement and disablement in Explorer. For more information on other cookie settings offered in Internet Explorer, refer to the following page from Microsoft: http://windows.microsoft.com/en-GB/windows-vista/Block-or-allow-cookies

_Google Chrome_

  * Click on the ‘wrench’ icon on the browser (usually found top-right corner) to open the tools menu
  * From the tools menu select ‘Options’
  * Click the ‘Under the Hood’ tab from the menu on the left.
  * In the ‘Privacy’ section, select the ‘Content settings’ button
  * To disable cookies: select ‘Block all cookies’ option
  * Note there are various levels of cookie enablement and disablement in Chrome. For more information on other cookie settings offered in Chrome, refer to the following page from Google: http://support.google.com/chrome/bin/answer.py?hl=en&answer=95647

_Mozilla Firefox_

  * Click on ‘Tools’ at the browser menu and select ‘Options’
  * Select the Privacy panel
  * To disable cookies: Uncheck at ‘Accept cookies for sites’ 
  * Note there are various levels of cookie enablement and disablement in Firefox. For more information, refer to the following page from Mozilla: http://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/Enabling%20and%20disabling%20cookies

_Safari on OSX_

  * Click on ‘Safari’  at the menu bar and select the ‘Preferences’ option
  * Click on ‘Security’
  * To disable cookies: In the ‘Accept cookies’ section select ‘Never’
  * Note there are various levels of cookie enablement and disablement in Safari. For more information on other cookie settings offered in Safari, refer to the following page from Apple:  http://docs.info.apple.com/article.html?path=Safari/3.0/en/9277.html

_All other browsers_

Please look for a “help” function in the browser or contact the browser provider.
